hello and welcome to the Jack Hopkins
Show podcast I'm your host Jack Hopkins
now before I introduce today's guest I
want to ask you a
favor don't worry it's it's not a huge
favor one of my episodes has almost
60,000
views but I've got just
6,300 subscribers and what that means is
a lot of people who are watching my
podcast episodes aren't
subscribed why does that matter in short
the greater my subscriber
numbers the more likely it is that I can
get and feature even more guests on my
podcast guest that you want to hear from
and that's good for you and it's good
for me as well so if you haven't already
please like And subscribe and I thank
you in advance now let's get to today's
guest for today's episode today's guest
is John kiraku John is an American
Author journalist and former CIA
intelligence officer he was jailed for
what the CIA called exposing the
interrogation techniques of the Central
Intelligence
Agency much of the world however had a
different view John kiraku was a
whistleblower on the torture program the
CIA had been running
and that Gina haspel later testified to
Congress had existed Gina haspel was the
seventh director of the
CIA now John was an intelligence analyst
and operations officer for the cia's
counterterrorism Center Senior
investigator for the Senate Foreign
Relations Committee and a consultant for
ABC News he was the first US government
official to confirm in December of
2007 that water boarding was used to
interrogate Al-Qaeda prisoners which he
described as
torture look you are in for a treat I I
just finished this episode and I already
can't wait to get him back on again so
without further Ado let's Dive Right In
to this episode with the fascinating and
intriguing John kiraku
all right John listen I I've got to tell
you I've probably
learned as much about world history from
you as as anyone else uh you know in so
many of the questions that you
answer uh I've always just been blown
away at your grasp of of world history
and in instead of answering something
within the context of say the you know
the last 5 to 10
years you're able to go way back and I
find that most of the time when you
provide that additional context oh okay
well this this all looks different then
within this right right yeah good point
hey may I tell you a quick story on that
very issue sure um I had just returned
from the Middle East this was like
1996 and I was assigned to Mentor a
brand new Junior analyst really really
smart young woman she had just graduated
from the University of Virginia and she
was covering the United Arab Emirates
and nothing ever happens in the UAE
we're close friends with the UAE it was
just someplace where she could learn you
know the writing style and
such well sure enough Iran uh invaded an
island off the coast of Shara which is
one of the the seven Emirates of the
United Arab
Emirates um it's actually two islands
it's called greater tun t NB and lesser
tunb so Iran had greater tunb sha had
lesser tun and the Iranians took it and
this island is like you know a mile by
two miles nobody lives on it or
anything and I said to her just
offhandedly we're just chatting and I
said um the UAE government's never going
to do anything to get that Island back
they're just going to concede it to the
Iranians and she said why why would they
do that
and I said
because the island is owned by Chara and
they don't give a [__] about charara
because it's a minor Emirate and I said
look foreign policy is run by by Abu
Dhabi and business policy is run by
Dubai and in
Dubai much of what they trade is with
Iran so why upset the apple cart over a
little tiny Island that only has a
couple of goats on it right so the
charin are just going to be [__] out of
luck
she goes into the uh into the boss's
office and she comes back out and she
sits down and she says I just resigned
and I'm like what why did you do that
and she said I realized that no matter
how much I like the job I'll never know
as much about it as you do I said that
is ridiculous I said I have a degree in
Middle Eastern studies you'll pick it
all up you're really smart and she said
no I just realized this just isn't for
me
that's that's wild and so my question
then is I'm guessing you were always
kind of a history buff yeah always and a
Middle East Buff when I was 15 um the
Iranians uh raided the American Embassy
and took our our people hostage and I
was just fascinated glued to it yeah and
you might remember that that led to the
creation of Nightline right so Nightline
on ABC was meant to give us the daily
update on on the situation with the I
didn't know that yeah and then you know
when there were no updates to give it
became a nighttime news program and then
lasted for for decades wow how much did
that benefit you as someone in the CIA I
I can only imagine immensely yeah
immensely is the word I but I was very
fortunate though Jack in that I knew
when I was 15 what I wanted to do when I
was nine I told my parents I wanted to
be a spy when I grew up and when I was
15 I had decided that I wanted to be a
spy in the Middle East when I grew up
and so I looked for universities that
had specific programs in Middle Eastern
studies at the time there were only
three there was briam young and they did
it just to teach their wouldbe
missionaries Arabic there was buters in
New Jersey and I just didn't want to go
to school in Newark and um and George
Washington University which was
literally one block from the white house
that's where the action is yeah and so I
went to GW I was one of only three
students enrolled in the in the Middle
Eastern studies program there but worth
every single minute and I was able to
specialize that became um that became
something that the CIA was looking for
in in the late 1980s and I got lucky so
you showed up with what you needed I I
was ready to go yeah yeah yeah you
know I I've got to tell you something
that I've multiple times when watching
you on other
podcasts and I've heard you talk about
this
some but anytime you go a different
direction than maybe what I'm thinking
not in terms of predicting what you're
going to say but in terms of like uh
being on the same page as me and you go
a different direction the thing I'm
always aware
of is that because I like you so
much my ears I I'm I'm paying attention
and I'm you know I don't go into that
defensive mode is that something about
yourself that you recognize
early on that that you could get people
to warm up to you quickly no frankly
really no in fact it's funny that you
bring this up because I was on the job
I'm going to say like six weeks so this
is February early February of
1990 and my boss I was I was an analyst
most analysts are um strong introverts
and I'm a strong EXT rovert but my boss
said to me you would be a good
operations officer and I said me why
would I be a good operations officer and
he said people like to be around you
yeah and I just thought well okay that's
kind of odd but all right well the
longer that I was in
analysis the more I realized that it it
wasn't really as great a fit for me as I
thought it was going to be cuz I
considered myself kind of an
intellectual you know I had bachelor's
and master's degrees I had multiple
foreign languages I was well
traveled um I would go to all of the uh
the uh events around town that the think
tanks were were
sponsoring and he's like no you're kind
of a fish out of water you should think
about operations and it wasn't
until you know 7 and a half years had
passed
and I got bored with analysis that I
decided to give operations a try yeah
and did you find almost
immediately maybe when you compared
yourself to your your colleagues or
other people on that side of the CIA
that wow I I'm good at this oh you know
what one of my station Chiefs and this
was in a big active major station
um pulled me
aside and he said um over the course of
my 30-year career he said I had five
recruitments and I remember every single
one of them he said you've been here two
years and you have five
recruitments and I said yeah you know as
crazy as it sounds I kind of have a
knack for this yeah and he said whatever
you're doing just keep doing
it I I I would assume
that gives you a a level of confidence
going into an operation once you've kind
of built that Foundation of trust of
your ability to do that yeah it became a
joke you know we we would have these um
classified staff meetings in the um the
embassy's uh it's called a bubble uh
what it is it's a tempest um U
secure room where you can speak freely
there's a double wall music is pumped in
between the walls and you know you you
can't intercept anything there kind of
like a skiff it's like a skiff but but a
mini yeah that's a good way to say it
it's a mini
skiff so
um my immediate boss uh had this had
this thing that he did whenever somebody
made a recruitment he would congratulate
them in the staff meeting and then toss
them a Snickers bar
that was your award for for making a
recruitment you got a Snickers
bar and there
was you know sometimes it takes you a
month sometimes it takes you a year to
recruit somebody and it just so
happened that I recruited three people
in one week and wow not that you know I
did all the work that one week it took
me a year a year and a quarter to get up
to that point and it just so happened
that they all came to a had that one
week so he said uh you know uh like to
congratulate kiraku for recruiting you
know MK Grasshopper And he tosses me a
Snickers bar and everybody you know
congratulations like to uh congratulate
kiraku for recruiting uh you know MK um
orange and people are like
okay uh and kyaku gets a third one for
recruiting so and so and one of the
other guys is like dude
stop and I said I it it was just one of
those weeks sure you're making us all
look bad and we're not going to get
promoted it's like I'm
sorry that's wild you know I I've never
heard you asked this question that I
know of and that's not to say I've
watched there may be some out there I
haven't seen when you are working in the
Middle East
how relevant is
your personal skin
tone that's a good question um and no I
haven't been asked that uh I
found especially when I was younger and
I didn't have this gray hair and it was
much thicker than it is I fit in almost
everywhere I went and my Arabic was so
good at the time people would ask me are
you Lebanese cuz you kind of speak with
a yemeni accent but you're too tall to
be
yeny um so the ability to fit in uh
helped me immensely and I'll tell you
one thing it was so funny I was invited
to a uh rotary club meeting in Abu
Dhabi and um the Ambassador was there
the deputy chief of mission and the
political officer all legit State
Department people so they're all sitting
at the same table and I decide to sit
with the Arabs right I don't want to sit
with the guys that I that I work with
all day long sure so I'm sitting with
the Arabs and one of these Arabs says to
me look at this look at this table over
here and he points at The Ambassador the
deputy Ambassador and the political
officer he says
CIA and I said yeah how can you tell he
said the CIA guys always sit together
and I said Muhammad that's exact exactly
why I'm sitting with you well
interesting by the end of the year I had
recruited Muhammad and he's like holy
[__] I would never have guessed it wow
yeah yeah and and you know what's always
fascinating to me about those types of
things uh we always think of the CIA
most people I would assume is based on a
lot of Hollywood right right and and
it's not right and I've got some
questions for you about that
that's one little thing that you would
think those guys made that mistake you
know what I me know right right right
yeah F but
um was that something that prior to him
saying that that you'd kind of notice
too that you know I guess you had
because you said you know who wants to
sit with the people you work with all
day yeah and yeah but you know my
station Chiefs from my very first
station chief he said
he
said well he said something that I later
added to when when I was training you
know young officers um he said
that when you go to an event you must
come back with a fistful of business
cards otherwise why go to the event
right to have free you know or derves
right seriously sure and and then later
on in my career there there was an
officer that I worked with we were were
in the same branch and she was just not
cut out for this job she was really
smart she had gotten a bachelor's degree
at the University of Michigan and a
master's degree from Yale
but smarts doesn't always translate into
being a good CIA officer right you have
to be manipulative you have to be able
to think quickly on the Fly sure so she
was doing her operational meetings and
then she would go back and they would
they would ask her so what did you learn
she is like he didn't really have
anything to say well then you've got to
terminate the contract right tell him
look this isn't working out thanks for
thanks for your time here's here's
$1,000 you know going away
present so I said to her one time my own
personal rule is if you go to an
operational meeting and you come back
and you don't have at least two
intelligence reports to write you have
failed the the agent didn't fail it's
not his fault that you didn't ask the
right questions you have failed and then
the station chief called me into her
office and she said I know what your
workload is but can you go with this
officer to her next operational meeting
and you do the meeting and you teach
her how to elicit the information
because she's failing and I said sure So
we went to the meeting and um had a nice
conversation about 2 hours and you know
we order some room service and there's
coffee and we're we're laughing and
talking and it's more of just a friendly
conversation than it is anything else
and then at the end of the two hours the
guy got up and we shook hands and he
walked out and she goes you see what I
mean he just doesn't say anything
important and I said I got four
intelligence reports out of that
conversation and she said how and I said
let's go over it so said he said this
and then he said B and then he said c
and then he said D he's talking about
proliferation he's talking about a
shipment of chemicals that's going to
you know the port of Rotterdam he's
talking she goes what do I know about
chemicals I said he told us what the
chemical was I don't know about
chemicals either but maybe it's a
cocaine
precursor maybe it's a chemical weapons
precursor what do I know right you put
it in elligence report and you let the
analysts figure it out she's like I
never thought of it that way so I wrote
out reports
yeah yeah she was okay and is that
something in your
experience for the most part you've
either got it or you don't or you don't
yeah that's exactly right and you know
one of the things that I learned
relatively early on in my career was
when people come into the CIA already
having phds they almost always fail
interesting
because for
example your PhD you've just finished
writing a 300 page dissertation and you
are the world's leading expert on this
issue that's so narrow that literally
nobody else in the world gives a [__]
about it but you think you're so smart
because you have a PhD okay well the
president doesn't give a [__] about your
opinion on such and such an issue the
president wants the entire thing boiled
down to half a page with three bullet
points so if you can't adapt to the
cia's writing style and tell the
president only what he absolutely needs
to know in order to form the most Cent
policy then you're failing and you
probably should go into journalism or
Academia not intelligence yeah
interesting I I knew a guy when I was a
kid back in the 70s and I had the
privilege of growing up around a there
were a bunch of World War II vets still
around you know wow oh that's very cool
you know yeah really um and
interestingly enough there was part of
me that had an awareness even at that
age of how significant this opportunity
was and and um there was a guy I I don't
think he went School Beyond 8th grade
right Old World War II vet and he could
take a fairly complex
subject and condense it down into two or
three sentences that would give
you the enough of the foundation of it
that you understood it enough to want to
pursue more
knowledge not everyone can do that
you
know I had much smarter people
educationally and IQ wise talk to me
about the same
thing you know I remember um during my
analytic uh stint in that first seven
and a half years something happened in
Kuwait and I had to write I had to write
something that used to be called a
snowflake so the president's Daily Brief
starts off with the most important
breaking news of the day and that's a
page and then Pages 2 three and four
are each page has two issues and each
issue gets two paragraphs fact and um
analysis okay so here's the breaking
news on page one Pages two three and
four that's six more short stories and
then you know at the the very back of
the book is um sort of the long longterm
big picture things you're allowed to go
two pages on those but then at the very
very end is something called a page of
snowflakes they they no longer do this
George HW Bush absolutely loved the
snowflakes because they were directly to
the point of a story a story that wasn't
important enough to put at the front of
the briefing so there were hard and fast
rules about snowflakes they had to be
three separate
thoughts um interrupted by ellipses do
dot dot and they could not be more than
36 words so you'd
say
uh Queen of England died today dot dot
dot uh Prince Charles expected to take
the throne by noon tomorrow dot dot dot
there will be no change in British
foreign policy toward the United States
that's a snowflake okay
so one of the leaders that I was
covering in the Middle East had what is
colloquially known as a nervous
breakdown there there is no such medical
condition as a nervous breakdown it's
just a it's just a word that that we all
use right so or a term
so I went to him and I said hey I wrote
a flake for the president because uh you
know he he knows this leader very well
they're on the phone all the time and
here here it is it was like 30 words and
you know King so and so had a nervous
breakdown and I put
parenthesis uh not parenthesis uh
quotation marks around nervous breakdown
because I knew he would object to the
term because it's not a medical
term and he's like yeah I don't I don't
uh you have to coordinate with all the
other analysts who who cover the same
issues so that there's agreement where
you know the entire intelligence
Community agrees that this this is this
situation so he's like yeah I can't uh I
can't agree with this I'm going to have
to make a couple of changes I said yeah
make whatever changes you want you're
the psychiatrist he was a psychiatrist
with both a an MD and a PhD in
Psychology so um he he sends it back to
me it has 56 words and I said Larry we
can't we can't send this the president
has 56 words he said yeah but I need 56
words to explain the situation and I
said we can't send it they will not send
it to the president I mean you and I can
write 5,000 words they're not going to
send it to the president
36 words and so it actually had to go up
through the chain of command and they
just went back to my
original thing with the quotation marks
around fascinating fascinating it's
interesting and I don't I'm think it's
probably not at all for the same reasons
but when I write my newsletters and it's
it's nothing I was ever taught obviously
that no English teacher would ever teach
you this I rarely use commas where where
I would have a comma I put dot dot dot
ah because in my mind and I've had some
feedback from from
subscribers a
comma doesn't necessarily
do translate into doing what it's
supposed to do which is kind of create
that separation but but dot dot
dot forces you to do it because the
distance your eyes have to track a
distance before they pick up again so it
it almost forces the reader into a pause
so um yeah that's just fascinating that
that's how you had to write those
snowflakes you know getting back to the
issue of the
phds they just could not adapt to that
kind of writing style they could not
adapt to not putting in their own
thoughts about you know whatever
happened to be happening around the
world it's like nobody at the White
House giv this [__] about your thoughts
right just lay out the facts you can put
your thoughts at the very
end
and I of all the phds I met who who came
into the CIA with the PHD only one
actually made it as a career the other
ones just just ended up walking out I'm
I'm sure you there's a good chance you
would agree that you met more operatives
without the educational background
ground who were better psychologist than
some of the phds God oh my God you know
it's funny when when you're going into
operations you have to take a an
enormous battery of psychological exams
because they want to make sure that you
have the right personality to do
something like this um and they want to
make sure that you um are able to
operate sometimes under extreme pressure
extreme pressure cuz not just while
you're doing the job but you're doing
the job while somebody else is trying to
sh shoot you you know and it's it's no
wonder everybody has PTSD but um but I
was very
um I was very taken when I got my
psychological exams back um I tested
right smack in the center of this bell
curve in terms of personality type but I
tested much
smarter than the average um operation
officer and I I kind of made a joke
about it with the hiring officer and he
said you know you make a joke but but
seriously um these tests tell me you're
going to be
successful because you already know the
issues we just needed to make sure that
your personality could handle the
pressure and and I could yeah and
assuming you were a good student in high
school all through I was yeah to come
pretty much come natural to you in terms
of you didn't run into things or you're
like oh my God I I can't do this I tell
you what trig in chemistry yeah tripped
me up but I didn't really care about
trigonometry and chemistry I wanted to
be a spy sure and my my intent was to be
a spy and so that's really all I focused
on or cared about yeah shift gears here
for a minute it's perhaps one of the
things you are most known for but I
don't think I've ever heard anybody ask
you this specific question was there a
key
moment where you knew you were going to
become a whistleblower was there a was
was
there yeah and I and I wish I could tell
you it it's because you know on
principle I stood up and I decided it
was nothing like that
um Brian Ross called me from ABC News in
early December
2007 and he said that he had a source
who said that I had tortured Abu
zubeda I said that was absolutely untrue
I was the only person who was kind to
abua I said I've never laid a hand on
abua or on any prisoner
ever and he said well you're welcome to
come on the show and defend yourself I
said yeah I'll think about it but then
that week two things happened President
Bush gave this is George W bush gave a
press conference in which he looked
right in the camera and he said we do
not torture like
that and I happen to be sitting with my
wife who is also a senior Cia officer
and I said he is a bald-faced liar he is
looking the American people in the eye
and he's just lying to us and
then that Friday
he was walking from the south Portico of
the White House to the helicopter to fly
to Camp David and a reporter shouted a
question about torture and he stopped
and he turned and he said well if there
is torture it's because of a rogue CIA
officer and I said to my wife Brian
Ross's source is at the White House and
they're going to try to pin this torture
program on
me I was opposed to it from
2007 I mean I'm sorry from 2002 this was
2007 but I had kept my mouth shut
thinking somebody is going to come out
and say something right but nobody did
and it was that moment when Bush stopped
and said Rogue CIA officer that I
decided I'm going public and I I I
decided in the days between my call to
Brian Ross and The Day of the interview
that no matter what he asked me I was
going to tell the
truth and it goes without
saying you were fully aware of potential
consequences I
assume you know I I actually wasn't and
in my own defense I'll tell you why I
wasn't it is a felony in the United
States it's actually in the US code it
is a felony to classify a criminal
act right you can't classify a program
if the program is violation of US law
torture was clearly illegal we have laws
going back to
1946 saying that exactly those those
methods that we were using were outlawed
right and I thought going public is not
revealing classified information because
it's illegal to classify a torture
program um the FBI investigated me for a
full year from December of 2007 to
December of 2008 and then wrote a letter
to my attorney um saying that they were
declining to to prosecute me
because it was illegal to classify a
crime um but then a month later when
Barack Obama became president John
Brennan convinced Eric Holder to
secretly reopen the case against me and
then they had
me wow it was
ugly
when did you have any colleagues
who
were surprise supporters and backers
when this all went down were were there
any people who you would have never
guessed in a million years that they'll
they'll put their reputation on the line
to to back me yeah there was one in
particular he was a retired deputy
director of the CIA I had worked for him
at the very start of my career and I
tell you he was a mean
SOB but he and I went to the Middle East
once together I went as his you know hat
holder um he was I'm not exaggerating
when I tell you he was eight grades
above me that's how senior he was so I
went as his hat holder and his his
um uh Note
Taker and
uh we went to a country that I had
covered very closely and he was
impressed with the
depth of knowledge that I had in this
country and its politics so he liked me
even though he was a mean son of a gun
he liked me I mean we could hear him in
his office like screaming swearing at
people I heard him fire a guy one time
just screaming like a crazy person and
then he announced he was going to take
two months off as a sabatical well you
can't you can't do that but this is what
they were telling everybody two months
off as a sabatical and then I heard
through the grape vine that he was
actually taken two months off to donate
a kidney to his sister his sister was D
wow so I emailed him from my private
account to his private account I said
what a wonderful thing you know heal
quickly you're a role model God bless
you for what you're doing for your
sister well
that that just aced it for the rest of
my career so when I blew the whistle he
emailed me he had just retired and he
emailed me the next day
and he said you have chosen a difficult
path but I'm glad somebody did I only
wish I had had the guts to do it
myself and I saved that email as a kind
of souvenir that I wasn't crazy I wasn't
a
traitor I had done the right thing yeah
yeah and I guess goes without saying
that you had people who you might have
thought would be supportive who ran the
other way oh listen I had relatives who
ran away from
me yeah
relatives you really you really get to
understand who your friends are truly
who they truly are when something like
this happens how have you
stayed not just then but but even now
how have you stayed connected to your
own North Star so to speak
with this
Duality
existing uh I'm going to answer that
question by um by telling you an
anecdote that I give at colleges and
universities when I speak there I always
use this example because I've always
thought it was so
powerful so I say let's say you are a
CIA operations officer and you have
recruited a Bonafide terrorist Al-Qaeda
Bala Isis bad guy yeah and you meet with
him once a month at a hotel in the
Middle East and this guy has given you
actionable intelligence that you have
used to save the lives of
Americans so you fly out to meet with
him and at the start of the meeting he
says to you you know what I've given you
everything that you've wanted and today
you're going to do something for me
you're going to go out and you're going
to get me a prostitute or I'm not
talking to you ever again so I ask give
me a show of hands how many of you will
get him the prostitute and usually about
80% put their hands up and I say yeah
you would give them the prostitute it's
unseemly it's dirty it's gross but this
is the job that we've chosen so you're
going to go out you get him the
prostitute what if he asks you for a
child
prostitute would he you do and people
will kind of look around discreetly and
then like 10% will
gingerly put their hand up and I say
absolutely
not not under any
circumstances but see here's the rub
there's no rule remember your job
overseas is to break the law right your
job is to get somebody to to commit
treason or espionage for
you headquarters isn't going to care if
you go out looking for a child
prostitute but listen some things really
are black and white right or
wrong and getting a man a child
prostitute is just wrong so you have to
go into this job with your own moral
compass you have to go in with your own
set of personal ethics because they're
not going to teach it to you there are
no ethics classes at the CIA yeah I and
to to rephrase a little bit what you
said about this your job is to break the
law I part of that could be construed by
some people in the CIA as my job is to
be as unethical and immoral as is
required to and you will bump up against
lots of officers who've taken that
position yes yeah yeah
so without your own s solid set of
values and your your own North Star so
to use that um you can go off the path
really quick I'm assuming oh yeah yeah
most definitely you really can and you
know over the years too you read in the
papers about oh so and so a CIA officer
was uh arrested and charged with rape or
charged with embezzlement or charged
with this or charged with that because
they really believe believe that they're
the good guys under any circumstances
and they can get away with anything they
want to get away with they don't have
that that moral compass they're just in
it for themselves they're in it for
their own gratification whether it's sex
or money or fancy watches or you know
whatever and and they get
caught which leads to a question I this
is a question I've really been wanting
to
ask is there a gray
area between sociopathy
and a
good CIA oh most definitely most
definitely I've said this uh many times
uh in podcast but I think it Bears a
repeating the CIA actively seeks to hire
people who have sociopathic
tendencies not sociopaths because
sociopaths have no conscience and
they're impossible to control and they
just blow right through the polygraph
exam you don't want people people who
have no conscience somebody with a
sociopathic tendency does have a
conscience does react in the polygraph
but because we're supposed to be the
good guys is willing to work in legal
moral and ethical gray areas right
interesting I I will will relate a a
personal story when I first showed up at
the naval special Warfare Center for
Buds and I I I I was not a seal I did I
was had a spinal injury and with Med
dropped early on so I I I W make that
clear I was not a seal but I showed up
at Buds and we're running inform
formation one
day and one of my class leaders uh went
on to work I think on a joint terrorism
task force for the Obama Administration
Jeffrey Edgars was his name and
um you know so you you you've got a
couple of guys usually are uh Academy
guys who are your you know the the class
officers and we're running in formation
one day and I I don't know who
initiated the
Cadence but the Cadence was throw the
candy in the courtyard watch the
children gather around Lock and Load
your
MP5 blow those little down now let me
tell you what went on in my head at that
point I I've always been pretty
self-aware and I
realized this
group we're not like other people mhm
most other
people
um it not that
I thought oh yeah shooting kids that
that's cool it wasn't that but it was
that I was I sang the
Cadence and that none of us looked at
each other like that was
strange and I thought you know I came
into
this
knowing what what the job is and and so
have uh both consciously and
unconsciously
accepted that that role that Duty and so
I I as I went on through life and and
pursued the psychology
uh I was very aware that I was not a
sociopath of course but I'm I'm very
clear that I I do have sociopathic
tendencies or I would have probably
never have wanted to go there in the
first place yeah how how many people
show up
there knowing that about themselves
almost none really I think that they
don't even really consider it in fact I
I tell this one story but I but I only
realized its Import in retrospect so
when I was being interviewed for the for
the job this is this is 1989 I'm being
interviewed for the job and um there are
like four other men and one woman and
we're given this scenario let's say that
you're serving
overseas and um you get a cable from
headquarters and they
want um they want some figures on the
Indonesian economy okay so go out and
collect it so you start targeting the
Indonesian second secretary for economic
Affairs at the
embassy and you take them to lunch you
hit it off you take them to dinner you
have a great time you introduce your
wives your wives get along you start
going to day trips together maybe you go
for a weekend together but after all
this development you come to the
conclusion that he's just not
recruitable but headquarters needs that
document so what do you do so one guy
raises his hand and he says well
headquarters wants the document so you
have to double down and you have to you
have to just keep doing what you're
doing until finally he's willing to turn
over the document and then this woman
raises her hand and she says well maybe
you can get the wives more engaged and
maybe you can get the document through
the wife and I'm looking around as
they're answering answering their their
answer and I'm like I put my hand up and
I said you break into the embassy and
you steal it and he says that's exactly
what you do you break into the embassy
and you steal it well that's a
sociopathic tendency a normal person
wouldn't Advocate breaking into a
foreign government's Embassy and
stealing documents but we're the good
guys and this is for the greater good
and you know USA
USA but that's what a sociopathic tend
is I didn't know that was a sociopathic
tendency it just seemed like a logical
answer to me would would you agree that
without good
people who have sociopathic tendencies
we'd be in trouble yes because then all
you're left with is a criminal
organization right you know that that's
a mob family you're you're describing
not an intelligent service sure change
your topic here again I know you've got
a timeline
today what are to the extent that you
can and I realize there are some things
you just can't talk about but to the
extent that you
can what are I'm this a two-part
question first
what is a surveillance
method that for its Simplicity was
surprisingly
effective that's a great
question um I was always partial to
foot
surveillance um you know when you're
working in a big City a capital city
usually traffic is terrible anywhere in
the world traffic is terrible so it's
better to do it on foot unless you're
willing to drive way out into the
Boondocks to do your to do your meeting
so one thing that was easy and very
effective was a technique that the CIA
calls stair
stepping so if if you're looking at a
map and a a stair step is you go
straight one block make a right go one
block then make a left one block then a
right one block left one block right one
block and so it looks like a like a
staircase right but every time you go to
cross the street you look both ways to
cross the street but you're really
looking for
surveillance gotcha and so they don't
know where you're going and you're
making all these
turns but you're acting very normally
and you're just looking to cross the
street and then you cross the street and
then you make a left and then you make a
right and then you make a left and make
a
right spotting surveillance couldn't be
any easier than that that's fascinating
and and again so simple yeah very simple
doesn't cost anything part two of that
then is what's something that you were
taught or picked up regarding
surveillance that was surprisingly
ineffective Ive in in real
time that was
surprisingly ineffective yeah dead
drops really
yeah I was bad at dead drops for a while
it was the only thing in training that I
struggled
with um I mean it sounds easy you just
you know you put the message you know
underneath the foot Bridge or you put it
under a rock or whatever
uh I had a colleague who put one inside
a condom cuz who's going to touch a
condom you know sure but um they're far
more complicated than just that so what
you do for a dead drop is first of all
you have to identify a place that's
suitable for a dead drop but if you're
in a sophisticated country like the
United States or Russia or China or Cuba
or Israel or even you know France or you
know places like that that have really
sophisticated intelligence Services just
being able to identify a place for a
viable Dead Drop is very very difficult
number one number two let's say you have
a place for a viable Dead Drop you've
got to do several things first you do a
two or thre hour or in the case of
Russia or China an8 hour surveillance
detection route to make sure you're not
being
followed you go to the Dead Drop you
make the drop then you do a surveillance
detection route either back to your
house or to your office so you do 2
three 5 8 hours to the drop and two
hours back that's a full day that's a
full work day yeah just to you know drop
a document or something W number
two then you have to do a surveillance
detection route to a predetermined site
to make a chalk
Mark so that you tip the agent to know
that there's something waiting for him
at the Dead
Drop so just to leave a single document
or a piece of microfilm or you know a a
microphone or a photograph or whatever
it is you're dropping at the drop site
you're talking about a 16-hour workday
oh yeah yeah yeah well that's not
practical yeah what's interesting about
that is that A simple piece of chalk
being part of a fairly well I'll tell
you what in in training this really got
me this is the only time I was
criticized in training okay so we're
training in Northern Virginia and I have
a dead drop site that's little bit
farther out in the Boondocks um I found
a rock
um I I I had a a fake rock that you can
put a key in you know people put them in
front of their houses and it it was the
same color the same shape as real
rocks in the parking lot of an office
building way out in the Virginia suburbs
so
perfect so you know I put the message in
there just throw it in with the other
rocks and um and tell the agent you
know this is where it
is so then I I do the surveillance
detection route to lay down the rock I'm
not being
followed and then I go to start my
surveillance detection route to the
place where I'm going to leave the chalk
Mark so I had chosen a an underground
parking garage in Tyson's Corner
Virginia well in the week or so what I
was supposed to do is just take a chalk
and just make a mark on on the door
leading from one level to the stairwell
right right in the week between when I
picked the site and when I actually went
there to make the mark they had painted
the doors okay no big deal the door was
the door was yellow when I went now it's
blue okay I don't care but they used
glossy paint oh and the chalk couldn't
make a
Mark and I was just going like this and
the chalk is just falling apart and it's
just not adhering to the door and so the
agent never knew that I that I left the
the drop and they were like listen you
fail not only did you fail but
surveillance saw you going like this on
the door like a crazy
person you would probably had this been
in a hostile environment you probably
would have been arrested and
expelled so that was such a valuable
lesson for me I still remember it today
and I'm talking this was this was 30
years ago yeah and those are the things
I I guess you know there are probably
multiple things you encountered in your
career that they can't possibly cover in
your training because there was just so
many variables that could happen and
that's where they rely on you to figure
it out yes yes
yeah I I know you've got to go soon so
I've got one last question for you sure
to to the best of your
knowledge and based on your
experience what do you think the current
state of our intelligence
agencies is in relationship to our
adversaries and are we at any increased
danger or are things maybe even better
and we just don't know where are
we well keeping in mind that I left 20
years
ago um I think there are areas where
we're better than everybody else and I
think there are other areas where we're
lagging um on technology we're cutting
edge and we know that thanks to the
Vault 7 uh Revelations I mean there is
stuff that just blew my mind in the in
the vault 7 Revelations I had no idea
the CIA was involved in and they're
quite Advanced working with NSA and
DARPA and gchq and the Canadians the
Australians the new
zealanders they've developed they've
developed technologies that we can't
even
fathom where they're
weak is in their understanding of
foreign cultures and foreign
languages especially
Chinese I would be absolutely
shocked if the CIA had more than a half
a dozen case officers who spoke passible
Chinese really M just like just like on
on September 11th 2001 there were only
like 16 of us in the entire CIA who
spoke
Arabic I mean that's
inexcusable and and how does that happen
John
how it can't I I can't think that it's
due to a a lack of foresight is there
something the awareness is there but it
just doesn't happen or yeah yes the
awareness is there and it doesn't happen
think of it this way um you are a CIA
manager and you've got these guys doing
operations working for you um and you're
told Hey listen this hot shot case
officer who's doing all these
recruitments and uh getting Awards
you're going to have to put him in
language school for 12
months and then he's going to go
overseas and you're not going to see him
for three more years well what manager
wants to give up as good people so they
could go sit in a classroom for 12
months and so they say ah we're going to
make an exception you're going to go
overseas without the
language well that might maybe work for
you it probably won't but it could but
then the agency loses because it doesn't
have enough people speaking these
languages right after September 11th um
they made a real effort to bring in new
people who spoke and I still remember
the languages they wanted they didn't
want to train people they wanted you to
come into the agency with Arabic farsy
Dari pashu uru Cindi Punjabi USC tajik
Korean Chinese and Russian
if you could speak any of those
languages you went to the very front of
the line but you know here we are
still
um with uh you know with with a shortage
of of hard language speakers and and
what do you do and I'm guessing Chinese
is maybe one of the tougher ones to
learn
absolutely absolutely they don't want
people who learned Spanish French and
German in high school that doesn't help
anybody and if you want to if you want
to focus on you know counternarcotics or
something then go work for the DEA with
your Spanish nobody cares right they
want those tough languages
yeah
finally have the kind of changes that
you had hoped would be implemented as a
result of your coming forward as a
whistleblower H have they happened on a
level that you had hoped they would um
yes and no um yes in that there is no
torture program anymore I'm I'm proud to
say that I had an integral role in that
I'm proud of it uh John McCain said so
on the floor of the Senate and when uh
Gina haspel uh appeared before the
Senate intelligence Committee in her
nomination hearing she admitted finally
that the torture program was a mistake
so yes in that respect
right on the other hand as recently as 3
weeks
ago um a batch of new hires was given a
a
slideshow uh with my picture on one of
the slides and it said underneath The
Insider
threat so CIA computers now um are using
AI to predict if and when an employee
might be thinking about becoming a
whistleblower so they can nip that in
the bud and there is a reward system for
CIA employees to rat out their
co-workers if they think a cooworker
might be thinking about blowing the
whistle on waste fraud abuse or
illegality so one step forward and two
back yeah the implication there just
your your picture and inside threat to
me if I were new trainee there I would
take that
partially as a a reinforcement of this
is you don't do this ever yeah and and
that that's that's a conflicting message
I would think that's right yeah that is
exact listen
I maybe someday you you will be willing
to come back and do this again because I
I've got so many things I would like to
talk to you about and my pleas my
pleasure that would be fantastic listen
thank you so much I know you've got to
go than invitation we'll do this again
sometime looking forward to it thank you
sir take care